hi everybody welcome back to today's
video I'm Nick this is polar ice
Creamery and today we are going to do
another video about ice cream
stabilizers this time it's tapioca
starch corn starch CMC GMS and finally
tarun I did a big stabilizer video what
over a year ago now and it's my most
popular video because people want to
understand more about stabilizers and
ice cream how to make them last longer
what they do to your ice cream and all
those kind of things so there's a lot of
different stabilizers out there uh some
are much more available in certain parts
of the world so going down this
stabilizer path I wanted to make sure
that I covered all the bases so that no
matter where you are in the world and we
have subscribers literally all over the
world you can access a decent stabilizer
for your ice cream to a improve texture
improve mouth feel and improve the
longevity of your ice cream in your
freezer as well so without further Ado
we're going to start with tapioca starch
or before we actually progress I just
want to say hi
to he's cool isn't he yeah some people
say he looks like me not enough gray
hair for that anyway we're going to
start with tapioca starch and cornstar
so starches are a very popular
stabilizer in Asia they're easily
accessible most of them actually are
produced over there as well which is
interesting whether you think it or not
what we're going to do is I'm going to
split the screen in half and we'll do
one half for tapioca and one half for
cornstarch the left hand side will have
tapioca starch right hand side will have
corn corn starch we're going to put up
the chemical breakdown or the chemical
structure of each one now it's not quite
as simple for cornstarch because there
are different versions depending on the
different elements that make up the
cornstarch but here we go you can see
there are some
similarities tapioca starch is derived
from the roots of the cast of a plant
and corn starch is extracted from the
endosperm of corn kernels
the flavor and texture of either this is
where they get a bit different tapioca
starch has no flavor and also imparts a
very glossy finish so if you're doing
something like a pie filling with
cherries and you want to keep that
really nice clear finish tapioca starch
is the way to go cornstarch on the other
hand has a strong Flavor now you see
online people say that it has no flavor
that's absolute BS corn starch has a
very distinct taste and when you use it
in recipes you can tell it's
there if you look online at bloggers and
vloggers you'll see that they use corn
starch in their luxury hot chocolates or
they Italian hot chocolates and things
like that now in Italy yes they do use
corn starch but they also use other ways
to thicken their hot chocolate as well
you go too far with that cornstarch and
you gra this really powdery unpleasant
taste to whatever you're making corn
starch also does not end clear it has an
opaque finish to whatever it is that
you're using to thicken so you may or
may not want to use cornstarch depending
on what your final result needs to
be the gelling properties of tapioca and
corn starch differ as well
they tapioca starch is very good at
slightly lower temperatures but it does
not hold up well to continual Heating
whereas corn starch can take continual
heating very very well so if you're
doing something that needs to be
processed at a high temperature a long
period of time you would avoid using
tapioca starch because it would break
down the elements that make it thicken
the source and then it won't go any
further and to some degree will actually
start reversing whereas cornstarch can
take that continual heating at a much
higher temperature without affecting the
final result tapioca starch and corn
starch are basically identical in the
fact that they are both
glutenfree and people use them often in
baking where a gluten-free result is
required because they can improve some
of the textures of some glutenfree
flowers that's it's quite difficult for
me to say glutenfree flowers so that's
our basics for tapio starch and corn
starch we'll go into a little bit more
conversation about them at the end but
what we're going to do now is move on to
CMC
CMC CMC stands for carboxymethyl
cellulose and the cellulose is extracted
from a couple of
organic methods or products but mainly
wood so what you're doing is you're
taking a wood byproduct and they're
extracting the cellulose from that and
then treating it to produce this white
powder it is a complicated process so
I'm going to put a list up on here
that will show exactly what is involved
with making
CMC so first you start with your
cellulose source and like I said
predominantly it starts from wood fibers
then you go through an an alkalization
process where the extracted cellulose
undergo alkalinization to make it more
reactive and this usually involves
treating it with an Alkali such as
sodium
hydroxide the next stage is
etherification where
carboxymethylation occurs through the
induction of carboxymethyl groups to the
cellulose chains this is done by
reacting the alkalized cellulose with a
sodium mono
chloroacetate the next stage is the
neutralization so after the carboxy
methylation has been done the product is
neutralized to obtain the sodium salt
form of
CMC and then the final stage is the
purification and drawing where the
carboxymethyl cellulose is purified and
dried to produce the final CMC powder
that you would buy in the
stores so as you can see it's not a
simple process and both CMC and GMS
really start to push the boundaries of
what's a natural stabilizer to some
degree everything needs to be processed
there are very few things in this world
that don't need to be processed but we
are getting into the Realms of
multi-stage chemical reactions to
produce something specific now CMC is a
generalized stabilizer so it will hold
on to that free water it will stabilize
your fat and water Emulsion it will
increase over runnability it will
improve mouth feel to a degree and it
also AIDS overrun much higher than some
other stabilizers would but it can
become quite fake and artificial at that
point one of the big downsides to CMC is
it's got quite a strong taste it it does
impart a flavor onto your ice cream and
if you're making a light flavored ice
cream then you you're going to struggle
you know because although flavors are
dulled in Dairy and that's just the fat
content if your flavor of whatever it is
you're making let's say you're making a
nice strawberry ice cream natural
strawberries broken down mated with some
sugar you've added your mix into your
Dairy base you've already lost some of
that strawberry flavor from that point
on if you then introduce CMC as your
stabilizer you're losing more flavor
because that CMC will impart its own
flavor over the top so you need to be
careful when you use CMC CMC is often
used in conjunction with GMS and that's
where we're going
[Music]
now
GMS glycerol monaster that is what it
stands for again this is really pushing
the boundaries for something that would
could be described as a natural
stabilizer but GMS is more of a multif
fire than a stabilizer and that's why
she often used in conjunction with the
CMC because it can stabilize your ice
cream on its own just not very well but
it is actually a reasonably good
emulsifier is it any any better than
less thin no I don't think it is but
each to own so without further Ado let's
pop our screen up and go into the
details of how GMS is made so GMS or
glycerol monasa is a synthetic compound
derived from glycerol and steric acid
both of which can have natural and
synthetic sources so glycerol or
glycerin depending on how you want to
describe it is a trihydro sugar alcohol
that can be derived from animal or plant
sources and it's commonly found in fats
and oils and can be obtained from
sources like vegetable oil or animal
fats then you have the second part which
is steric acid steric acid is a
saturated fatty acid that can be found
in various animal and plant fats and it
can be derived from sources such as
cocoa butter coconut oil or palm
oil the synthesis of GMS involves the
reaction between the glycerol and steric
acid leading to the for leading to the
formation of glycerol mono
sterate so when used in combination with
CMC GMS can have a pretty good result
but it seems to be that the cheaper ice
cream brands use CMC and GMS and that is
likely because they can get it in much
higher
numbers so we're now going to go on to
our final one for today which is
tarum
tarum has got a Resurgence over the last
few years because it's quite expensive
as an ice cream
stabilizer and I'm going to put a
picture up here on the screen of a Tara
tree and this tree is native to Peru and
other South American countries the Tara
tree itself produces pods much like
locust bean gum and it is actually
processed in very similar SAR ways too
so it's dried ground down and then
filtered to produce this white powder
that you use tarum is excellent because
it it does two different things it will
stabilize and has emulsifying thickening
elements as
well
so tarum though is
expensive it's difficult to get a hold
of and it is
expensive if you are in North America
you're going to struggle to get
it which is strange because there are it
does grow in some parts of the US on the
west coast but considering it's it's
closest to the US than a lot of other
parts of the world I don't understand
why it's so expensive to get in North
America but it is but it also is one of
the best Standalone stabilizers I'd
probably actually say it is the best
Standalone stabilizer that you could use
so if you were to look at Standalone
stabilizers such as zanam gum guar gum
and tarum of those three tara gum is
definitely
first and then there's you know personal
opinion over zanth gum and Gua gum
because they're really quite similar but
it really boils down to between those
two whether you need to heat the base or
not if you don't need to heat the base
then you know you you've got cold
process both of them great but if you
are heating the base get good gum will
thicken much harder and much quicker so
again it comes down to personal
preference but what exactly does tarum
do here we go up with our little box
again it is a texture improver and
that's because it increases viscosity
and as we know and have learned over the
years that an a slight increase in
viscosity will increase the creaminess
and mouth feel of your ice cream it is a
stabilizer so it prevents the separation
of water and fats in your mix which also
is what an emulsifier does so this is
why tyam is really really good it
reduces Ice Crystal or large Ice Crystal
formation much like locust bean gum does
and it is really good at it too and with
that in hand your ice cream is much
better in the mouth with small tiny ice
crystals with large ice crystals it's
icy and horrible okay so tarum will help
to keep that ice Crystal size down that
as a byproduct then gives you a much
nicer mouth feel and it also helps with
your overrun as well so it will increase
your overrun but not as much as some of
the others like CMC would but it does
help you get a little bit more out of
your home machine as we have established
home machines don't really give you the
same amount of overrun that a commercial
machine will so you might only get 20%
15% out of some of the machines some of
the home machines you you're going to be
lucky to get 5% overrun
but the reality of it is if you use
something like tarum a CMC you know
xantham gum Gua gum you will then
increase your overrun which will give
you a slightly lighter ice cream much
more in tune with what you would buy
from the likes of henar and Ben and
Jerry's and ample Hills and Jenny's
Etc and it starts to produce a more
natural ice cream the dense pudding like
ice creams with sub 20 15% overrun
very dense very hard to scoop I mean
they do taste great when when you
actually get them out but it's a balance
isn't it you can get much more ice cream
out of your mix with a slightly higher
overrun of say 30 to 40% which is about
industry standard for for store-bought
ice creams the cheaper Brands obviously
as we know and have established we get
to 100% And even higher and that's when
the names change from Ice Cream to
frozen
dessert but what we've done done now is
we've just gone over the next group of
stabilizers and out of all of them that
we've discussed tapio starch and corn
starch I personally don't use in ice
cream I don't find the a I don't like
using corn starch and ice cream because
it imparts that flavor tapioca
starch just doesn't have the same
efficiency as some of the some of the
other stabilizers so you can buy it it's
cheaper but it it really does struggle
to to thicken control the ice it will
definitely thicken so it will increase
viscosity but it just doesn't do a good
a job as good a job as controlling Ice
Crystal formation and improving mouth
feel and overrun so I generally don't
use the starches and ice cream but if
that's what you have available then
stick to tapioca starch as opposed to
corn starch a because it doesn't have a
flavor B it's
probably a bit easier to dissolve and
incorporate and see you can concentrate
on the viscosity rather than how much
flavor your powder is going to add CMC
and
GMS if that's all you've got available
then go for it you know that they will
do the job they will do the job
reasonably well you have to use both you
have to combine CMC with GMS but if
you're into the more natural approach to
stabilization and by natural approach I
mean using natural products that go
through probably one process of drying
powdering processing like Locus bean gum
tara gum you know that kind of thing
zanam gum then I probably would avoid
CMC and GMS but again there are certain
parts of the world that both of these
are likely the only options available to
you so if you do use those again
consider balancing that out so you would
want to start somewhere along the lines
of a 6030 60% 30% ratio of CMC to GMS
and play with that depending on what ice
cream you're making some flavors of ice
cream will do better with more emif fire
like chocolate ice cream really needs
more emulsifier than than others some
vegan recipes will definitely need more
emulsifier because of the separate
sources of fats and the type of fats
that you're using so if if you're going
to start looking at vegan recipes then
you really need to concentrate on the
best ways to stabilize and emulsify your
recipe and it's a big difference when
you when you do plant-based
recipes one of your main fat sources
will likely be something like coconut
oil if you use deodorized coconut oil
which I do because I don't like all my
plant-based recipes to taste like
coconut then you need a way to stabilize
that fat and make sure that the
emulsification between that coconut fat
sauce and
water predominantly being what's in your
nut
milks again they're 1% to 3% of fat the
rest is mostly
water then you need to look at an
emulsifier to make sure that those two
water and fat elements are really well
joined and combined and don't separate
down the line so the emulsifier will
join the two together and it will help
to keep it stabilized but then you have
the stabilizer and it will help to keep
that chain strong over the whole process
and not separate when it's in the
freezer and then finally tarum like I
said I love tarum it's great I I don't
use it that often in recipes um because
I ran out back in the UK and I've just
had to import it over from Europe it's
turned up um we're going to start using
it and I'll explain a little bit more in
each video as I do it if you want me to
talk about what stabilizers I use in
each recipe then let me know in the
comments because I change it up almost
weekly I will use a different stabilizer
for a different recipe to see the result
you use the stabilizer that you have
available to you if you're unsure and
you're using something like starches you
will need a lot more tapioca starch or
corn starch than you would for any of
the other stabilizers because that's
just their process you know they need a
lot more to stabilize the free water so
if you're in doubt pop in a comment send
me an email and
will make sure that you can create the
best ice cream possible with the
ingredients that you have available
where you are and don't listen to
everyone say You must use this and you
must use that no that's
rubbish I I had a guy argue with me
until he was blue in the face losing his
temper left right and Center because he
demanded that it was better to use Gua
gum locust bean gum you know it it's
rubbish you use what you have what you
want if you don't want to use
stabilizers don't use them your ice
cream are going to deteriorate a little
bit over time you know there's no two
ways around that but that's just what
will happen but if you do want to use
stabilizers then there are premix
available you know I love the special
ingredient stabilizer it's great is it
perfect no but is it really good yes and
will it do the job every time yes it
will tara gum is like that as well zanam
gum is like that g gum is like that you
know but they have pros and cons so
balance this video with the first
stabilizer video and your individual
ones for zanam gum g gum Locus bean gum
balance those videos out determine what
is available to you and how best to use
it again if you're unsure pop me a
comment and I will help you but you need
to let me know what ice cream you're
making let me know more details so I can
help you create the best ice cream that
you can all right so with that in mind
thanks very much for watching hopefully
this second stabilizer actually is the
second big stabilizer video but
hopefully these stabilizer videos are
helping you at home creating to create
the best ice cream that you've ever had
I mean the comments that I get from
people is incredible people love the
turn that their ice cream making at home
has taken after joining in this ice
cream family and what can I say you know
I am here to help you all create the
best ice cream you can with the least
fuss so thanks very much for watching
don't forget to like And subscribe
subscribe and I'll see you next time
when we make another delicious ice
[Music]
cream